A Guide to the Lexington Arsenal and Virginia Militia Records, 1702; 1793-1839
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Lexington Arsenal and Virginia Militia Records 1702; 1793-1839
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00244
The collection contains 47 items filed in one box.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 1816 the Virginia legislature provided for the establishment of three arsenals to care for the state's accumulation of munitions. One of the three was constructed in Lexington, Virginia, on the site of what is now the Virginia Military Institute. The arsenal opened in 1818 under the command of Captain James Paxton, and the guard stationed there was responsible for approximately 30,000 stand of arms. Although the size of the detachment stationed at the Lexington Arsenal varied somewhat from year to year, it generally consisted of the captain, a sergeant, one or two corporals, ten to thirteen privates, and a few employees among whom were musicians. This arrangement was maintained until 1839, when the Virginia Military Institute opened on the site of the arsenal and the arsenal guard was replaced by the new VMI cadets.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of two series. The first series contains miscellaneous records (1702; 1793-1814; 17 items) relating to the Virginia Militia, including regimental returns for various militia units. This material pre-dates the establishment of the state arsenal at Lexington, Virginia, but the documents were found among the Lexington arsenal records also contained in this collection. Two of the documents date from the British colonial period (1702).
The second series (1819-1839) contains 30 items concerning the operation of the state arsenal at Lexington, Virginia. Included are payrolls and other financial records, guard returns and muster rolls, and two enlistment documents.
Contents List
- Virginia Militia Records, 1702; 1793-1814
  This series contains regimental returns for various Virginia Militia units and miscellaneous other documents relating to the Virginia Militia. This material pre-dates the establishment of the arsenal at Lexington, Virginia, but the material was found among the Lexington Arsenal records also contained in this collection. Two of the documents date from the British colonial period (1702).
  - Regimental Returns
    Chronological.
    - 53rd Regiment, Campbell County. 1795 November 10
      "A return of the Militia in the 53d Regiment in the County of Campbell commanded by William Henderson, together with a return of arms etc. belonging to said Regiment."
    - 91st Regiment, Bedford County, 1796 June 16
      "Return of the militia in the 91st Regiment in the county of Bedford commanded by John Trigg Lieut. Col. Commandt., together with a return of arms etc. belonging to said regiment."
    - 91st Regiment, Bedford County, 1796 November 4
      "Return of militia in the 91st Regiment in the county of Bedford commanded by John Trigg Lieut. Commandt., together with a return of arms etc. belonging to said regiment."
    - 43rd Regiment, Franklin County, 1797 November 10
      "A return of the Militia ordered to be in readiness to march at a moments warning from the 43 Regiment Franklin County. Samuel Hairston, in the absence of Col. John Early."
    - 53rd Regiment, 1798 October 30
      Signed by Daniel B. Berrow, Colonel.
    - 18th Regiment, Patrick County, 1799 June 13
      "A return of the 18th Regiment of Militia, Patrick County, State of Virginia, including the Arms, Ammunition & Accoutrements in their possession, George Penn, Lt. Col."
    - 64th Regiment, 1799 October 15
      "A return of the sixty fourth Regiment being part of the twelveth Brigade of the Militia of the State of Virginia, including the arms, ammunition, & accoutrements in their possession."
    - 91st Regiment, 1802 June 9
      "A return of the 91st Regiment being part of the 12th Brigade of the Militia of the State of Virginia, including the arms, ammunition, & accoutrements in their possession."
    - 53rd Regiment, 1802 November
      "A return of the 53rd Regiment being part of the 12th Brigade of the Militia of the State of Virginia, including the arms, ammunition, & accoutrements in their possession in Nov. 1802."
    - 110th Regiment, 1802 December 10
      "A return of the 110th Regiment including the arms, ammunition, & accoutrements in their possession, Samuel Hairston Lt. Col. Com."
  - Militia Appointment Documents
    - John Foster, 3rd Regiment appointment, 1793 September 23
      Signed by Governor Henry Lee. Appointing John Foster from Orange County Ensign in the second Battalion, Third Regiment Militia.
    - John Foster, 3rd Regiment appointment, 1797 December 11
      Signed by Governor James Wood. Appointing John Foster "Ensign of a company of Light Infantry in the third Regiment, and Second Division."
  - Other Militia Documents
    - British documents estimating cost for Arms etc. for "Colony of Virginia," 1702 April & June
    - Receipt, Robert Patterson, 1808 May 31
      "Two pounds, two shillings & nine pence"
    - Regimental Morning Report, 1812 October 19
      "Regimental Morning Report Colonel Dudley Evans, Joseph Allen Adjutant, Total 686."
    - Regulations, Published, regarding Uniform, 1814 April 4
      Issued by Adjutant General's Office, Richmond, Virginia, re: "changes in the uniform of the Army of the United States."
- Lexington (Virginia) Arsenal Records, 1819-1839
  The state arsenal at Lexington, Virginia opened in 1818 and operated until November 1839, when it was replaced by the Virginia Military Institute.
  - Financial Records, 1822-1839
    - Payroll Records.
      - Payroll of the Public Guard, Lexington Arsenal, 1822 November-December
        Names on the payroll: James Paxton (Captain), Samuel Lasley, Rodk [Roderick?]King, John Spooner, James Barnett, Alexander Briant, John Mays, James Hening, Wilford Downs, David Craig, Benjamin Downs, James Edsal, Elias Wood, William McCrery, Ezekiel Kirby, Andrew Hincher, Thomas Jones, John Short, James R. Collins, James Smith, Jessee Pannal, James Page, William Brown, Chesly Woodard, William B. Smith, Benjamin Bowler, Granvill Doores.
      - Payroll of the Public Guard, Lexington Arsenal, 1826 September-October
        Names on the payroll: James Paxton (Captain), Wilfred Downs, William H. Knap, James Smith, William Suthard, John Clark, Silas Rogers, Archibald Downey, William Lewis, John Mays, Henry Peterman, Angus McLaughlin, Michael Robinson, Thomas Johnson, Fayette.
      - Payroll of the Public Guard, Lexington Arsenal, 1830 November-December
        Names on the payroll: David E. Moore (Captain), Jacob Moses (Sergeant), John T. Giles (Corporal), Andrew Gass (Corporal), Thomas Burton, Elijzh Coomer, John Davis (1st), James Barron, William Cunningham, Jospeh Hockman, John Masterson, James Smith, William Suthard, John Davis (2nd), [illegible]
      - Payroll document for Private William Suthard. 1834 August
        For period March 1- April 11, 1834.
      - Payroll, Lexington Arsenal, 1837 May-June
        Names on payroll: David E. Moore (Captain), John Oringderff, Richard Anderson, Valentine Franklin, Thomas Anderson, Berry Epperson, John Flint, Andrew Gass, Joseph Hockman, John Pavo [Povo?], James Robinson, Thomas Smith, Benjamin F. Steele, James Vandegraff, Isaac Walton, James H. Wiglesworth, George W. Rowsey, Daniel Ward, Jack.
      - Payroll, Lexington Arsenal, 1837 September-October
        Names on payroll: David E. Moore (Captain), John Oringderff, Richard Anderson, Valentine Franklin, Thomas Anderson, Berry Epperson, Samuel Flint, Andrew Gass, Joseph Hockman, John Pavo, James Robinson, Thomas Smith, Benjamin F. Steele, James Vandegraff, Isaac Walton, James H. Wiglesworth, George W. Rowsey, Daniel Ward, Jack.
    - Accounts, 1823-1839
      - Return of extra days work done by the guard.... 1823 June 21
        Letter of explanation on reverse; signed by Captain James Paxton.
      - Subsistence and Clothing Account for Capt. James Paxton, 1826 September-October
      - Subsistence and Clothing Account for Capt. D. E. Moore, 1830 July & August
      - Account statement, Caruthers & Alexander, 1832-1833
        For various sundries & dry goods, including material for a shroud for John Pointer.
      - Account book, 1832-1839
        A bound volume, primarily accounts for provisions and rations.
      - Subsistence and Clothing Account for Capt. D. E. Moore, 1834 May & June
      - Subsistence and Clothing Account for Capt. D. E. Moore, 1837 September & October
      - Account, Bounties & Contingencies 1837 September & October
      - Statement, number of arms in arsenal, undated
        "The Arsenal at Lexington contains 30601 muskets, 1001 rifles, 87 carbines, 30 cavalry swords."
    - Receipts
      - Receipt, Nathan Carpenter, 1832 December
        For freight on box of clothing.
      - Receipt, John Darst, 1833 April 18
        For repairs to Lexington Arsenal
      - Receipt, J. Moses 1834 May & June
      - Receipt, Reuben Jackson 1834 June
        For payment as fifer.
      - Receipt, John [McKinsey] 1834 June 25
        Payment for freight.
      - Receipt, William Southard, 1834 August 13
        For clothing due on discharge.
      - Receipt, Jacob H. Moses, 1834 August
        For returning soldier E. McCraw who was in jail in Lynchburg.
      - Receipts, William Southard, undated
        Discharge bounty
      - Receipt, William Southard undated
        Final pay upon discharge.
  - Guard Returns and Muster Rolls, 1820-1838
    Some muster rolls are also located in the bound Account Book listed under Financial Records above.
    - Half monthly return, 1820 January 1-15
    - Half monthly return, 1829 September 1-15
      Appended to bottom is the note: "No recruits enlisted since last return. The following supply of clothing will be necessary for the guard at the arsenal during the ensuing winter..."
    - Half monthly return, 1830 November 15-30
      Includes note concerning the receipt of clothing.
    - Muster Roll, 1838 March-April
      Names on muster roll: D. E. Moore (Captain), John Orindorf, R. Anderson, V. Franklin, J. Vandegriff, T. Anderson, B. Epperson, Samuel Flint, J. Povo, G. W. Rowsey, F. G. Steele, William Smith, I. Walton, J. H. Wigglesworth, A W. Eaton, William Eaton, M. Slagle.
  - Enlistment documents, 1819-1820
    - Enlistment of Andrew Hincher [Hinchee], 1819 May 9
      "...born in the county of Rockingham ..aged 22 years, 5 feet 3 inches high...by profession a tailor...."
    - Enlistment of John Spooner, 1820 March 1
      "...born in the town of Coblentz and empire of Germany, aged 20 years, 5 feet 4 inches...by profession a tobacconist...."